All
right. בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we're on מסכת זבחים. Masechet Zvachim. We're
in דף י, Daf Yud, getting ready today to do דף יא.
Daf Yud Aleph. We're in דף י Daf Yud at the bottom,
four and a little bit lines from the bottom. End of the
line begins with
תנן התם: Tenan Hatam: שהיה רבי עקיבא אומר: Shehayah Rabbi Akiva Omer:
כל דמים שנכנסו להיכל לכפר פסולים.
Kol damim shenichnasu
laheichal l'chaper psulim. וחכמים אומרים: V'chachamim omrim: חטאת בלבד. chatat bilvad. רבי
אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: אף האשם, af ha-asham, שנאמר: shene-emar: כחטאת
כאשם. kachatat k'asham.
So we have three different opinions. Rabbi Akiva says any bloods
that entered the sanctuary makes the is unfit,
is פסול. pasul. וחכמים Chachamim say, the rabbis say, only חטאת chatat
has this stricture, and Rabbi Eliezer includes the חטאת chatat and
the אשם. asham. Rabbi Akiva brings backing from a later משנה Mishnah
in זבחים Zvachim in דף צא ב, Daf Tzadik Aleph Bet, where
there is a פסוק pasuk from פרשת צו Parshat Tzav from ויקרא
Vayikra that says: וכל חטאת אשר יובא מדמה אל אהל מועד לא
תאכל באש תשרף. V'chol chatat asher yuvah midamah el ohel moed lo
teachal ba-esh tisaref. Because it says for him וכל חטאת, v'chol chatat,
he sees like a double plural
so that it's not it's כל חטאת, kol chatat, so one there's
a חטאת, chatat, then there's more than that because of all and
and all, therefore he says any blood that comes into the sanctuary
will make it פסול. pasul. We just saw it on the bottom
of י ב. Ten Bet.
וחכמים V'chachamim say only חטאת, chatat, only the sin offering, and Rabbi
Eliezer says אשם כחטאת asham k'chatat and he we have a פסוק
pasuk for him because in ויקרא Vayikra 7:7
there is a היקש heikesh בין חטאת ואשם bein chatat v'asham and
we've seen it and we'll see it again.
We've seen it and we'll see it
again
and it's a big question in today's discussion when is חטאת chatat
like אשם asham and when is it different? I mean it's a
lot of our discussion anyway, when are the קרבנות, korbanot, when can
we learn from one to another, when are they the same and
when are they not the same? What kind of קל וחומר kal
vachomer can we make? Like I mentioned last time, all frogs are
green, maybe. So does that mean all green things are frogs? So
how which directions can we take our logic and our קל וחומר?
kal vachomer? Okay.
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, we just stated his opinion, we don't come
back to it at least not in this דף, daf, and we
continue and say: בשלמא bishlama רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer כדאמר טעמא, k'da'amar
ta'ama, we know his טעם, ta'am, אלא רבנן מאי טעמא? ela rabanan
mai ta'ama? What is the reasons that the רבנן rabanan say that
is only חטאת? chatat? אמר רבא: Amar Rava: אשם נכנס דמו לפנים
פסול לא מצית, asham nichnas damo lifnim pasul lo matzit, אמרת amart
קל וחומר kal vachomer מעולה. me-olah. So we don't have if I
understand correctly we don't have a specific place where it says about
the אשם, asham,
about the guilt offering, that if the blood enters the sanctuary it's
going to be פסול, pasul, but we're learning it from a קל
וחומר kal vachomer from the עולה. olah.
Top of יא עמוד א. Yud Aleph Amud Aleph. מה עולה שהיא
כליל נכנס דמה לפנים כשירה, Ma olah she-hi kalil nichnas damah lifnim
kshira, אשם שאינו כליל לא כל שכן? asham she-eino kalil lo kol
she-ken?
So we're going to try this. We're going to see if this
works it's not going to work. Okay.
So if the עולה olah can we keep the Hebrew names of
the sacrifices or do we need to translate them? No. It's complicated.
Okay. So if the עולה olah which is burned completely, if its
blood enters the sanctuary it's still kosher, so can we from that
is it like "oh, all the more so the אשם asham which
is not burned completely,
wouldn't that also be unfit when it enters the sanctuary?"
No. Like that's like a kind of like "yeah, right", like where
do we go with it? What? Okay, so not good. So let's
try a different one.
מה
לעולה. Ma l'olah. Because the עולה olah is here, oh, but
what
is this? שלמים? Shelamim?
Yeah, I know, but like where is the חטאת chatat not in
this circle?
You have to do your own Venn diagram.
Can I, can I? But like these are all תודות. todot. So
now, let's say the חטאת chatat and the אשם asham maybe are
here? Correct. Is here. Kind of. Okay.
So,
so in the previous קל וחומר kal vachomer we said, "Oh, the
עולה olah is burnt completely, so therefore the אשם asham also something
something." But they're like in different categories. So then the גמרא Gemara
refutes this. That was a lot of yesterday's דף. daf. I think
that's going to be a lot of this מסכת masechet now.
Let's see how we do. Okay.
מה לעולה שכן אינה מכפרת. Mah le'olah sheken einah mechaperet. It's like
the גמרא Gemara is like, "Whoa, what is, what does that have
to do with the עולה olah here? It's not, it's not מכפר,
mechaper, it's not one of the things that atones for a transgression."
We're in the top of י"א. yud aleph. מנחת חוטא תוכיח. Minchat
choteh tochiach.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, "Maybe we can learn something
from the מנחה minchah offering of a sinner, right?" So now these
are all זבחים, zevachim, these are all sacrifices of real meat. Okay.
We have two more sacrifices that are not here. Here is the
pen, right, the מנחה. minchah.
And I don't want to draw it, but let's say we have
a עוף of which will come in a minute too.
Right. Okay.
So we say מנחת חוטא תוכיח. Minchat choteh tochiach. So the גמרא
Gemara is like wondering, "Wait, ולימא חטאת העוף תוכיח? velayma chatat ha'of
tochiach? Why, why are you bringing me an example from a מנחה,
minchah, right, from a meal offering? We're talking about animals, so how
did you make that connection? Maybe we should bring it from birds."
I was going to say chicken.
Either or, שחוט. shechut.
Exactly. He says, he says, חטאת העוף בא דרבי אבין היא. chatat
ha'of ba deRabbi Avin hi. Well, first, this is like we're going
to have a problem with it because the birds have a different
process. The bird does not get שחיטה shechitah like animals from the
בקר וצאן, bakar vetzon, from
translation,
and it has a מליקה, melikah, right, where you break its neck
and then we don't do the same process with the blood, we
take it with a finger.
Okay. So we go back to try the מנחה. minchah. And we
say וליפרך מה למנחת חוטא שכן אינה מן זבח. velifroch mah leminchat
choteh sheken einah min zevach. So we already said the מנחה minchah
meal offering is not good because it's not a slaughtering offer. So
we go back to the עולה. olah. Basically, we go back in
the circle and we can't find a proof from this. We've kind
of driven ourselves into a corner.
וחזר הדין לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה.
vechazar hadin lo rei zeh kerei zeh velo rei zeh kerei zeh.
So this is not quite like that and this is not quite
like that. So now what are they like and what are they
different? הצד השוה שבהן. hatzad hashavah shebahen. This is the עולה olah
and חטאת chatat that they're considered קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim ונכנס דמן
לפנים כשר. venichnas daman lifnim kasher. אף אני אביא אשם שהוא קדש
קדשים ונכנס דמו לפנים כשר. af ani avi asham shehu kodesh kodashim
venichnas damo lifnim kasher. Okay, so in what way? Let's do this.
In what way is the עולה olah or the
עולה olah and חטאת chatat similar? They
are קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, right? They're not קדשים קלים kodashim kalim
which are maybe the בכור bechor or the מעשר ma'aser if I
remember correctly. So let me bring אשם, asham, אשם asham also can
be קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. But now it's a different category. Instead
of the thanks and the sin offering, then we'll try to divide
it this way. Yes? Mhm.
Can I ask you a quick question? I know I came in
late. What is the premise here is that if the blood is
brought into the sanctuary, the sacrifice is invalid?
Possibly. For some. For some, yes.
Okay, but what's that, what's, that's what we're trying to figure out.
No, I feel, I realize that, but what invalidates? Don't you have
to bring the blood in to put it on to?
No, because there's the inner altar, then there's the outer altar.
Two different, two different altars. Okay, so which, which are they talking
about?
Generally, most offerings are offered on the outer altar, but like those
that are brought in the inner altar, like let's say the שעיר
לעבודה זרה, se'ir la'avodah zarah, that kind of thing, and
the כהן גדול פר. Kohen Gadol par. Thank you Michael. Okay. Oy.
Okay. אמר ליה רבא מברניש לרב אשי Amar lei Rava MiBarnish l'Rav
Ashi ולפרוך מה לצד השוה שבהן שכן אין להן
קצבה תאמר
באשם שיש לו קצבה.
u'lifroch ma l'tzad hashaveh shebahen sheken ein lahen kitzvah tomar b'asham sheyesh
lo kitzvah.
So let's add another symbol to our fun thing here. אשם Asham
has money. Right? Has a minimum of what it has to be.
And the חטאת, Chatat, no.
And the עולה Olah also no.
So maybe from there we can find similarities and
there's
a minimum value, isn't there?
It's a minimum, but the עולה Olah and חטאת Chatat and מנחת
חוטא Minchat Choteh don't have a minimum, but the Torah was more
strict with the אשם Asham that needs, that has a minimum. Okay.
אלא היינו טעמיה דרבנן. Ella hainu ta'amei d'Rabbanan. Okay. דאמר קרא דמה.
De'amar Kra damah.
So we have a פסוק Pasuk that we saw in the beginning
that it says ובכל חטאת אשר יובא מדמה. U'vchol chatat asher yuva
midamah. Every חטאת, Chatat, every sin offering, that from its blood would
bring. So what do we do with this word דמה? Damah?
First the גמרא Gemara says דמה של זו ולא דמה של אחר.
Damah shel zu v'lo damah shel acher. By saying its blood, we
mean the specific blood of this and not a blood of something
else. What the אידך, Idach, what is Rabbi Eliezer, how is Rabbi
Eliezer going to respond to it? דמה ולא בשרה. Damah v'lo besarah.
He's not going to address whether it's this blood or somebody else's
blood, right? Because he's looking at חטאת ואשם Chatat v'Asham both of
them being able to have their blood in. So he says the
reference to דם Dam is because it implies
blood
but not meat, but not flesh.
Okay. ואידך, V'Idach, the Rabbis, how do they know, where do they
find the distinction between blood and meat? דם
דמה. Dam damah.
What do they learn from this issue of the דמה? Damah? They
learn actually two things. One like Rabbi Eliezer, that it's blood and
not meat that we're talking about, and the other thing which we
saw in the bottom of דף י' עמוד ב', Daf Yud Amud
Bet, that we're only talking about חטאת Chatat that makes the חטאת
Chatat פסול Pasul but the other sacrifices not.
Okay. ואידך, V'Idach, what again what is Rabbi Eliezer doing with this?
דם דמה לא דריש. Dam damah lo darish. So he doesn't, he
doesn't explain this פסוק Pasuk this way.
He thinks, we think he thinks, that the פסוק Pasuk needs the
word דם Dam because we are talking about blood and not just
about the חטאת Chatat offering in general,
and therefore the גמרא Gemara tells us דם דמה לא דריש, Dam
damah lo darish, like דמה Damah is the correct grammatical form to
use
here and therefore he learns from it that it's blood and not
meat.
Okay.
Back to back to our discussion. בשלמא לרבנן דאמרי אשם ששחטו שלא
לשמו כשר. Bishlama l'Rabbanan d'amri asham sheshachato shelo lishmo kasher.
So this is the discussion we have in this whole מסכת Masechet
which gets, it can get confusing.
Okay. אשם ששחטו שלא לשמו כשר. Asham sheshachato shelo lishmo kasher. If
we have a guilt offering and it's slaughtered not for its purpose,
whatever there was some other intent, it's still כשר. Kasher. It does
not exempt the person who brought it for the purpose he brought
it, but it's still, it's still כשר. Kasher. היינו דאיתקש מנחה לחטאת
מנחה לאשם. Hainu d'itkash mincha l'chatat mincha l'asham.
So we can make a היקש, Hekesh, we can learn here how
meal offering, the מנחת חוטא, Minchat Choteh, how sometimes it is like
a sin offering and sometimes it is like a guilt. Sometimes it's
like a חטאת Chatat and sometimes it's like an אשם. Asham.
Let's see. דתניא רבי שמעון אומר. Detanya Rabbi Shimon omer. Rabbi Shimon
brings us... Rabbi Shimon brings us a פסוק pasuk from פרשת צו
Parshat Tzav
from ויקרא Vayikra 6:10. קודש קדשים היא כחטאת וכאשם. Kodesh kodashim hi
kachataat vechaasham.
This is what we mentioned yesterday. מנחת חוטא הרי היא כחטאת. Minchat
chote harei hi kachataat. So it says, this is like a sin
offering. So let's see how. לפיכך קמצה שלא לשמה פסולה מנחת נדבה
הרי היא כאשם לפיכך קמצה שלא לשמה כשירה. Lepichach kamtza shelo lishma
psula minchat nedava harei hi kaasham lepichach kamtza shelo lishma kshira. Okay,
so sometimes this is my understanding here. Sometimes the מנחת חוטא, minchat
chote, the meal offering that is for a sin offering, sometimes it's
like a חטאת chataat and sometimes it's like an אשם.
asham. Well, isn't every מנחה mincha a חטאת?
chataat? If it's being brought for a מנחת חוטא minchat chote then
it's like a חטאת. chataat. Sometimes it's like a חוטא, chote, like
a חטאת chataat because it's brought like a מנחת חוטא minchat chote
and sometimes it's like an אשם asham because it's brought like a
מנחת נדבה. minchat nedava. Yes.
Okay.
And some of it has to do with the practice. We'll come
to it in just a minute. Okay. אלא לרבי אליעזר למי הלכתא
איתקש מנחה לחטאת ומנחה לאשם. Ela l'Rabbi Eliezer lemai hilchata itkash mincha
l'chataat u'mincha l'asham.
What is it for Rabbi Eliezer? לכי אידך דרבי שמעון. L'chi idach
d'Rabbi Shimon. He finds in it a different דין. din. דתנן שלא
בכלי שרת פסולה ורבי שמעון מכשיר. Detnan shelo bichli sharet psula v'Rabbi
Shimon machshir. Okay,
so pause for a minute. What
again? I'm happy for input. Okay. What are similarities from the זבחים
zvachim and the מנחה? mincha? There are four
עבודות הדם, avodot
hadam, four blood works that are done with the זבח zevach and
we've looked at it earlier in this מסכת. masechet.
שחיטה. Shechita. We would test everybody. Everybody remembers the four עבודות הדם.
avodot hadam. No.
Okay. שחיטה, Shechita, the כלי, kli, right, the קבלה, kabala, הולכה, holacha,
and זריקה. zrika. Okay,
so we slaughter the animal, we collect the blood, we walk it
and then we sprinkle the blood. Now the מנחה mincha has four
parallel עבודות avodot as well. So the מנחה mincha can be sort
of like meat but for vegan.
So there can be parallel offers that we can do without the
meat. What is parallel to the שחיטה shechita is the קמיצה. kmitza.
It's like whatever, collecting the offering.
That to me would be more like קבלה הדם. kabala hadam. How
is קמיצה kmitza like זביחה? zvicha?
This is like I'll tell you. This is what I can only
tell you what I learned. Okay. The קמיצה kmitza is like שחיטה.
shechita. Then there is a כלי שרת. kli sharet. I'll send you.
I saw
a rabbi I listen to on this one.
I still don't understand the connection.
If you'd explain it.
Hold on, hold on. I don't know if I can. Hold on
a second.
Let me give you the whole thing. Do you want me to
write it or do you want me to just tell you the
whole thing? Okay. The קמיצה kmitza is like שחיטה. shechita. The קבלה
kabala is like putting the מנחה mincha in a כלי שרת kli
sharet because the מנחה mincha needs a כלי. kli. הולכה Holacha is
הולכה holacha and the זריקה zrika is like putting it on the
fire and bringing it up. Okay. So I guess the קמיצה kmitza
is like preparing it, right? Because it's like you gather it in
order to put it in a vessel in order to carry it
in order to put it on the altar. And the שחיטה shechita
is kind of the same preparation in an animal.
Don't really see that.
But okay. It's the order that they...
Do you see it in a different way? I just see the
other three, I don't see the first one. Okay. Yeah. Well, anybody
can do the שחיטה shechita but it has to be a כהן
kohen who does the קמיצה. kmitza.
Correct. Can anyone put it in the כלי שרת? kli sharet? I
don't
know. Do you know?
I forget. But anyone can prepare all the rest of it beforehand.
Like you know you can prepare it and then you know bring
it to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
I think what I understood from that is that there is... and
you can elaborate more... we have קדושת דמים kdushat damim and קדושת
הגוף, kdushat hagoof, which the קרבן זבח, korban zevach, the meat sacrifice,
has like intrinsically. But for מנחה mincha you need the כלי kli
in order to have this added קדושת גוף. kdushat goof. And therefore,
therefore the discussion here, דתנן שלא בכלי שרת פסולה. detnan shelo bichli
sharet psula. It's a learning that we have from the מנחה mincha
into this discussion even though רבי שמעון מכשיר. Rabbi Shimon machshir. A
question in the back?
No. False.
Yes. Is it just the order? Is it just the order that
they
offer?
Well,
any...
They want to remind the
people.
They really want to
do this
parallel.
They're grinding the flour and
making sure it's סולת solet and
sifting it 13 times and all that. That's the real preparation of
the מנחה. mincha.
But
once you're there that's like the
end of it. Something else? No? Okay. That's that's I don't claim
to expert expertise in the קרבנות.
korbanot.
So it's
okay. Okay. Let me see where we are. Okay. ואמר רב יהודה
בריה דרב חייא, Va'amar Rav Yehuda berei de-Rav Chiyya, מאי טעמא דרבי
שמעון? Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Shimon? אמר קרא, Amar kra, קודש קדשים היא
כחטאת וכאשם. kodesh kodashim hi ke-chatat ve-ke-asham. בא לעובדה ביד, Ba le-ovda
beyad, עובדה בימין כחטאת. ovda be-yamin ke-chatat.
בכלי, Bikhli, עובדה בשמאל
כאשם. ovda be-smol ke-asham. So there's back to
the same
conversation. Right? When we say
קודש
קדשים היא כחטאת וכאשם, kodesh kodashim hi ke-chatat ve-ke-asham,
there's ways that it can be like a חטאת, chatat, there's ways
that it can be like an אשם. asham.
The חטאת chatat is performed with the right hand and the אשם,
asham, sorry, and the guilt offering is performed with the left hand
and so we can find parallels from both. ורבי שמעון, Ve-Rabbi Shimon,
האי קרא מפיק ליה להכי ומפיק ליה להכי. hai kra mapik lei
le-hachi u-mapik lei le-hachi.
How does he, what does he do with this, with this verse?
Does he take
it for which purpose is he, what is he learning from here?
The handful. הכא קרא לכדרב יהודה בריה דרב חייא הוא. Hacha kra
le-che-de-Rav Yehuda berei de-Rav Chiyya hu. So most of or the main
issue is how Rav Yehuda explained it. ואתא ומנחת חוטא דפסולה שלא
לשמה טעמא אחרינא
הוא. Ve-ata u-minchat choteh de-psula shelo lishma ta'ama
achrina
hu.
Okay.
And the and the הלכה halacha that the מנחת חוטא, minchat choteh,
that the meal offering is that the handful was removed is not
לשמה lishma is פסולה, psula, that's that's another reason. חטאת טעמא מאי?
Chatat ta'ama mai? דכתיב בה היא. de-chtiv bah hi. Where is our
פסוק? pasuk? קודש קדשים היא כחטאת וכאשם. kodesh kodashim hi ke-chatat ve-ke-asham.
So we have a word that repeats, the word היא. hi. Also
in regarding to the מנחת חוטא, minchat choteh, this is now we're
comparing contrasting two פסוקים, psukim, one from ויקרא Vayikra 4:24 and one
from 5:11,
where in both of them the word היא hi in Hebrew
appears.
So this is we learned that it has to be דווקא davka
לשמה lishma because that word really is not necessary. It could have
said קודש קדשים כחטאת וכאשם, kodesh kodashim ke-chatat ve-ke-asham, but it says
היא, hi, so that specifically. ולרבנן, U-le-Rabbanan, למאי הלכתא איתקש אשם לחטאת?
le-mai hilchata itkash asham le-chatat? Again,
we're asking the Rabbis, how do they learn it? לומר לך, Lomar
lecha, מה חטאת טעונה סמיכה אף אשם טעון סמיכה.
ma chatat te-una
smicha af asham ta-un smicha. So there is another way that they
are similar, the חטאת chatat and the אשם, asham, they both need
סמיכה. smicha. We both need a כהן. Kohen.
Yeah but
doesn't everyone agree to that? So then why do we stop over
here? Shouldn't we say what what does Rabbi Shimon do with that?
I don't know why we don't stop over here. I can't answer
that. It would be okay with me if there was some אגדתא
Agadata here in the middle.
You've got to wait until the very end, two דף daf before
the end there's only אגדתא.
Agadata. That's a good question. I appreciate the question. And I can't
help. All right. Okay. This is how we'll learn. Back to the
beginning of the מסכת. masechet.
We bring back a part of the משנה mishna from the beginning.
יוסף בן חוני אומר הנשחטים. Yosef ben Choni omer ha-nishchatim. And he
says in the middle of the משנה. mishna. on דף ב, daf
bet, יוסף בן חוני אומר הנשחטים לשם פסח ולשם חטאת פסולים. Yosef
ben Choni omer hanishchatim leshem pesach v-leshem chatat pesulim. Okay. Okay.
We learned this in the משנה mishna that anything that is done
for פסח pesach and for חטאת chatat is פסול. pasul. And in
some ways, this it can make it can make sense. The חטאת
chatat is to atone for a sin. So I can't I can't
change that. Like, there needs to be an atonement. I can change
between the thanksgiving ones. And on the nice chart there is a
place that they overlap. But the sin offerings are different. How do
I switch between them? And פסח pesach has extra חומרות chumrot where
it needs to be done at the right time with the right
intention with the people around eating from it. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabi Yochanan, יוסף בן חוני ורבי אליעזר אמרו דבר אחד.
Yosef ben Choni v-Rabi Eliezer amru
davar echad. רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan thinks about יוסף בן חוני Yosef
ben Choni and his statement and רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer that they
said the same thing. That not only חטאת chatat and פסח pesach
that were not done לשמן, lishman, were not done for their intended
purpose, are פסול, pasul, but all the קרבנות korbanot that are done
for the purpose of חטאת chatat and פסח pesach are are פסול
pasul as well. But רבה אמר, Raba amar, רבה אמר Raba amar
באחרים לשם חטאת פליגי.
bacharim leshem chatat
peligi. So רבה Raba slightly disagrees with
רבי יוחנן. Rabi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan says יוסף בן חוני
Yosef ben Choni and רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer are talking about the
same thing. רבה Raba says they're not talking about exactly the same
thing. They're talking about
the
same thing regarding פסח, pesach, that an עולה olah for the sake
of פסח pesach would be פסול. pasul.
But an עולה olah for the sake of חטאת, chatat, for רבי
יוסף בן חוני Rabi Yosef ben Choni it's פסול, pasul, for רבי
אליעזר Rabi Eliezer it's כשר, kosher, but it's just it didn't fulfill
the purpose. So the sacrifice itself is כשר, kosher, but not fulfilling
the חיוב. chiyuv. And Micah, I'll send you a link to the
rabbi I'm listening to as well. Okay. באחרים לשם חטאת פליגי, bacharim
leshem chatat peligi, דתניא. detanya. Okay. As we thought in the ברייתא.
baraita. Now we have a long discussion about this,
the פסח pesach and between רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer specifically and רבי
יהושע Rabi Yehoshua
coming
up.
And I don't know, I'm wondering how everybody else reads it, but
it's almost like רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer leads רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua
into an impossible place where רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua realizes that if
they go this route, it becomes an against the תורה. Torah. And
then it comes back and then like we close that discussion.
Yes, this is a note here.
This says this is according to רש"י. Rashi. But תוספות Tosafot oh,
you know?
No, no, go ahead.
תוספות Tosafot below on eleven B disagree with רש"י Rashi stating that
רבה Raba does not dispute רבי יוחנן's Rabi Yochanan statement, rather he
is elaborating on it. Okay. So how I don't know yet, we
haven't gotten there yet.
How he means
I don't know.
Okay. It's על פניו, al panav, like on the surface, it seems
like a מחלוקת machloket between רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan and רבה Raba
about how they understand the agreement or disagreement between יוסף
בן חוני Yosef ben Choni and רבי אליעזר. Rabi Eliezer. Let's see.
דתניא הפסח שעברה שנתו ושחטו בזמנו לשמו
וכן השוחט אחרים לשם פסח בזמנו
רבי אליעזר פוסל ורבי יהושע מכשיר.
Detanya hapesach she-avrah shnato v-shachato b-zmano lishmo v-chen hashochet acherim
leshem
pesach
b-zmano Rabi
Eliezer posel v-Rabi Yehoshua machshir. I just want to say, for me,
and maybe it's פשיטא pshita for everybody, there are there are three
options. Like usually we're contradicting two things, but here we actually have,
if I understand it correctly, you're welcome to help, there's three things,
right? A sacrifice can be כשר, kasher, it can be פסול, pasul,
and then it can be יוצא החיוב. yotzei hachiyuv.
Okay? So a sacrifice can be כשר kasher
but not יוצא החיוב. yotzei hachiyuv.
So for example what is יוצא החיוב?
yotzei hachiyuv? Oh, I I made a transgression, I bring a חטאת.
chatat. I have a wrong intention or something, so my sacrifice is
כשר, kosher, whatever, somebody can eat it, but I did not fulfill
my obligation, that's what it says, I did not fulfill my obligation
vis-à-vis my sin
because while I was doing it I was thinking about I don't
know something
else. Okay, so פסח, Pesach, but פסח Pesach has a very specific
time when it can be done and this is part of the
discussion. What if it's now August? I'm hungry. Let's do a פסח
Pesach offering.
Yeah, that's ridiculous.
So while there is no category for ridiculous, it can only be
one of these.
Well, a פסח, Pesach, you can't have a פסח Pesach except on
the 14th of ניסן Nisan or the 14th of
אייר.
Iyar. So again, four seconds, three at a time, not more. Okay.
If it got lost then it was a פסח Pesach that's for
the wrong time, not because we're saying just let's do a פסח.
Pesach.
Right. Yeah, like it was intended for a פסח. Pesach. Right. Designated,
didn't get done.
Right. We're doing it another time.
Gloria's same point? No, different point that in one of these previous
contexts we talked about if the wrong intent is so ridiculous we
just ignore the wrong intent. Okay, because it just can't be. So
we assume it was. So in your example of if it's August
and I'm bringing something for the first time, not a lost one,
and say let's make this a פסח. Pesach. I think that intent
maybe just gets the first time will go somewhere else.
But like in David's example, we found the sheep.
Right. It got lost. Right. Now we found the sheep. Okay. So
we'll see if the פסח, Pesach, if פסח Pesach has past time
it becomes a שלמים. shelamim. It becomes another kind of a thankfulness,
but not anymore פסח. Pesach.
Well, I'm glad we're all excited about. Yeah.
We woke up. Okay, let's see how this goes. דתניא. De-tanya.
הפסח Hapesach שעברה she-avrah שנתו shnato ושחטו ushechato בזמנו bizmano לשמו lishmo
וכן vechen השוחט hashochet אחרים acherim לשם leshem פסח pesach בזמנו bizmano
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer פוסל posel רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua מכשיר. machshir.
And now they're going to have a lot of back and forth
on which way can the קל וחומר kal vachomer go in order
to learn whether it's פסול pasul or כשר. kasher.
So first, well and then there's a question, what does כשר kasher
mean in this context?
Okay, can you actually can you eat it?
Yeah, I think you can eat it, but it doesn't fulfill your
פסח Pesach thing. It's like it becomes another form of a שלמים.
shelamim.
It's just a regular barbeque.
Yeah, which edible but not didn't do anything.
Okay.
Religiously.
Religiously. Is there another universe?
Okay, I didn't know but it satisfied his appetite. Huh? It satisfied
his appetite.
Right. It satisfied his appetite. Right. Okay, let's go into the discussion.
Yes.
אמר Amar רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua He's רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua is
now going to explain and it's going to be a little bit
of a rollercoaster so
let's
try to buckle up. Okay. אם Im בשאר bish'ar ימות yemot השנה
hashanah שאינו she'eino כשר kasher לשמו lishmo אחרים acherim כשרים ksharim לשמו
lishmo בזמנו bizmano שהוא shehu כשר kasher לשמו lishmo אינו eino דין
din שיכשירו sheyichshiru
אחרים acherim לשמו? lishmo?
Okay. So the פסח Pesach all year long is פסול. pasul.
Correct. Yes. פסח Pesach all year long is פסול. pasul. שלמים shelamim
for the sake of פסח Pesach or עולה Olah for the sake
of פסח Pesach is כשר. kasher. This רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer accepts
this too. Not on פסח Pesach itself but throughout the year. What
do we mean a פסח Pesach שעברה she-avrah שנתו shnato in the
previous thing? So we had what did we lose? A sheep, right?
And now a year or some months has passed by, it was
intended for פסח, Pesach, it becomes a שלמים. shelamim.
I think the
thing
there is it's got to be a good פסח Pesach it's got
to be under a year old, but during that time it was
lost it had its first birthday. Okay. Oh, so now
it's it passed the year.
Yeah. So maybe it got lost and found between פסח Pesach and
פסח שני Pesach Sheni and maybe you could have otherwise brought it
on פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, but it had its birthday in that
one year buffer.
Okay.
So according to this, to רבי יהושע's Rabi Yehoshua, thinking,
if the פסח Pesach for the sake of פסח Pesach on י"ד
Yud Daled be- ניסן Nisan
like in the appropriate time is כשר, kasher, maybe we can learn
from it or he says we can learn from it or is
it logical that we learn from it that also שלמים Shlamim for
the sake of פסח Pesach is כשר. kasher. שלמים Shlamim I
don't
even know where to add פסח Pesach there but the שלמים Shlamim
for the sake of פסח Pesach could be כשר. kasher. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer basically says something like if you if you
think you have a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, I have another קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, we could do it backwards or חילוף הדברים. chiluf
hadevarim. ומה אם בשאר ימות השנה שאינו כשר פסח לשמו,
Umah im bish'ar yemot hashanah she'eino
kasher Pesach lishmo, right, פסח Pesach is not כשר kasher in the
rest of the year, כשר הוא לשם אחרים, kasher hu leshem acherim,
he's not kosher for the sake of פסח Pesach but it is
kosher for the sake of שלמים Shlamim for something else. בזמנו שהוא
כשר לשמו אין הדין שיוכשר לשם אחרים? Bizmano shehu kasher lishmo ein
hadin sheyuchshar leshem acherim? Okay, the whole year it's not kosher for
its own sake
and it is kosher for others. So we can say the קל
וחומר kal vachomer backwards. When it is kosher for its own sake,
then קל וחומר kal vachomer it's kosher for others. Like
I keep giving the frog example, it's maybe it's probably not perfect.
ויוכשר Veyuchshar just finish his thing ויוכשר פסח בארבעה עשר שלא לשמו.
veyuchshar Pesach bearba'ah asar shelo lishmo. If you go with this, then
we will have a פסח Pesach that's not for its for its
sake, yes.
Which contradicts the הלכה. halacha.
And we've already concluded that that's not not possible.
But this is what I said earlier, and maybe I misunderstand it,
but it's like רבי Rabbi יהושע Yehoshua presents his reasoning and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, basically says, okay, if we go with this, then
this is מתבקש, mitvakesh, like this is what's going to come out.
ורבי יהושע VeRabbi Yehoshua is like, oh, okay, so I can refute
that. ורבי אליעזר VeRabbi Eliezer says, well, at that rate, we're going
to end up with things that are not הלכתי hilchati and we
already know they can't be done.
Okay, this is finely said correctly over there.
So now רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, brings his קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
clearly doesn't work. וכך אתה אומר, Vechach atah omer, this is what
you say, right. מה לי הוכשרו אחרים בשאר ימות השנה לשמו שכן
הוא כשר לשם אחרים ויוכשרו אחרים בזמנו לשמו שכן הוא פסול לשם
אחרים.
Mah li huchsharu acherim bish'ar yemot hashanah lishmo sheken hu kasher leshem
acherim veyuchsharu acherim bizmano
lishmo sheken hu pasul leshem acherim.
This is like you can't do it because the פסח Pesach
for the sake of other offerings is פסול, pasul, is not acceptable.
The פסח Pesach can only be done for itself. אמר לו רבי
יהושע. amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי Rabbi יהושע Yehoshua. says to him,
okay, if you want to go this route,
I have something I can refute what you're saying, because what you're
saying now, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer הורעת כוח פסח ונתת כוח
בשלמים. horata koach Pesach venatata koach bashlamim. If you're going that route,
then you diminished the validity, the power of פסח Pesach and you
gave more power to the שלמים Shlamim
because
okay,
so רבי אליעזר, Rabi Eliezer let me see if I can read
this. Yeah,
it's
they're trying to go two ways in a street that really is
one way. פסח Pesach offering
during the rest of the year is going to become a שלמים
Shlamim and is going to be כשר. kasher. But a שלמים Shlamim
sacrificed on פסח Pesach eve
is not going to be כשר. kasher. חזר רבי אליעזר. Chazar Rabbi
Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer says, okay, you're right.
And I don't know if he really leads him, but that's how
I read the conversation. ודנו דין אחר. Vedanu din acher. So he
teaches him or presents
a different
דין. din. מצינו מותר פסח בשלמים ואין מותר שלמים בפסח. Matzinu motar
Pesach bashlamim ve'ein motar shlamim baPesach. So okay, so what is מותר
פסח? motar Pesach? If we have leftover from פסח, Pesach, it can
become a שלמים. Shlamim. But if we have leftover from שלמים, Shlamim,
can it become פסח? Pesach? Never. Never. Okay, so let's just say
if I bought a פסח, Pesach, I whatever set aside $100, I'm
going to buy a פסח Pesach offering, I only used $80. What
should I do with the extra 20? I can bring a שלמים.
Shlamim. But if I got a שלמים, Shlamim, I cannot with the
change get a פסח Pesach offering
because it's already
intended what did you say designated for שלמים Shlamim I
cannot.
I mean an animal that was already designated as this, I say
זו שלמים, zo Shlamim, I can't turn that into a פסח. Pesach.
Okay, so now yes.
I'm thinking that a פסח Pesach is like a subcategory of שלמים
Shlamim with specific things.
So therefore, this is why I'm scared, I don't know where to
put it here.
No, no, no, it's correct.
Maybe it's its own little circle inside
שלמים, Shlamim, like here kind of thing. Exactly. It's maybe a little
bit of a תודה. Todah. Right. But it's not an עולה olah
because it's eaten.
We'll ask Rabbi tomorrow. Maybe this broken מצה matzah here is a
פסח. Pesach. Okay. ומה פסח שמותרו בא שלמים שחטו בזמנו לשום שלמים
פסול. Uma Pesach shemotaro ba Shlamim shechato bizmano leshum Shlamim pasul. Even
that the leftover like
פסח Pesach is for פסח, Pesach, so
שלמים שאין מותרו בא פסח אם שחטם לשם פסח בזמנו אינו דין
שיהיו פסולים. Shlamim she'ein motaro ba Pesach im shechatam leshem Pesach bizmano
eino din sheyiyu pesulim. So
the פסח Pesach offering, the leftover is brought like as a שלמים,
Shlamim, right? But if it's designated
for—my
God—if it's designated for the שלמים Shlamim then it's then it's
פסול. pasul. So too the שלמים Shlamim that can't have a leftover
be a פסח, Pesach, if you slaughter them for the sake of
פסח Pesach in its time, isn't it obvious that
they'll be פסול? pasul? Tan-tan-tan, suspense, what will Rabbi Yehoshua say? I
think
we
should re-enact these conversations and see if we can refute them the
same way. Okay.
Me and my notes.
Apologies here.
אמר לו רבי יהושע. Amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua. מצינו מותר חטאת בא
עולה ואין מותר עולה בא חטאת. Matzinu motar chatat ba olah ve'ein
motar olah ba chatat. Okay, so we we learn, right? That if
we have a leftover from a חטאת, chatat, if we have a
leftover from a sin offering, it can be burned completely as an
עולה. olah. But if we have a leftover from an עולה, olah,
can it be brought like a חטאת? chatat?
No. No.
Why not? There is no leftover.
It's burned completely.
So it's like like it can't go both ways, sorry. ומה חטאת
שמותרה בא עולה שחטה לשם עולה פסולה עולה שאין מותרה בא חטאת
שחטה לשם חטאת אינו דין שתהא פסולה.
Uma chatat shemotara ba olah shechata leshem olah psulah olah she'ein motara
ba chatat shechata leshem chatat eino din shetehei psulah. Like
okay, and if
the חטאת chatat that has a leftover for עולה, olah, if it's
slaughtered for an עולה, olah, it's פסולה, psulah, it's not kosher anymore.
The עולה olah that doesn't have the leftover and you want to
do it חטאת, chatat, of course it's going to be פסול pasul
as well.
So this—I have another—okay. So this is one of those things that's
ridiculous. A sin offering
is female
and עולה olah is male.
Okay, say more, not
yet sure what to do with it.
So an עולה, olah, so one cannot become the other.
It's not the same animal.
Oh, whereas the שלמים, Shlamim,
it could be the
שלמים Shlamim can be either male or female.
It can be the same animal and the פסח. Pesach. Right.
So is it like by just in principle that the leftover of
the חטאת chatat could be burned completely, could be brought up as
an עולה, olah, like in the same method?
I mean they must be referring to the money that you've set
aside because it can't be the animal.
Right, that's a good note there, then
you could purchase a different... okay, I'm guessing from this you could
wait until it develops a blemish and then sell it and get
the... yeah, this is about about a חטאת chatat and an עולה.
olah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So top of—even if—an animal the—you can't have the same animal go
from one to the other.
Okay, at
least for an individual עולה.
olah. אמר לו רבי אליעזר. Amar lo Rabbi Eliezer.
What does residual mean?
We're using the word residual and it's here
too also.
Residual חטאת.
chatat. Tiny bit leftover?
What
is...
That assumes it's already been שחט, shachted, right?
The nice thing what I understand is that רבי Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer
at this point should have said to רבי Rabbi
יהושע Yehoshua again—this would be for me, this would be good to
like study ten times and then get the feeling and also act
out the conversations and then see what everybody, what everybody's skin in
the game is, what are they fighting over. רבי Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer
should have said to רבי Rabbi יהושע, Yehoshua you're right. But now
he specifies and he says, look.
This is going to be the end of the discussion and this
is why I think, but again, maybe take out an alternate opinion
with explanation why it was like led into this so he can
prove his point. Okay, say. Sure.
So even, they even recognize this in the grammar here. It's for
a חטאת, chatas, it is מותרה, motarah, and for an עולה, olah,
it is מותר. motar.
So the
question is—I don't want to do this right now—but the question is
if we're talking about a קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, קרבן עולה. korban
olah. Right. So then the word
קרבן—but korban we saw earlier that we had דם, dam, דמה, damah,
and היא, hi, so we talk about a in a feminine, in
a female form of the language.
Let's not.
Okay, keep going.
Yeah, I want a little bit mileage for tomorrow.
Okay. אמר לו רבי אליעזר, Amar lo Rabi Eliezer, לא. lo. אם
אמרת בחטאת Im amarta b'chatas שכן כשרה לשמה כל השנה כולה, she'ken
k'sheira lishmah kol hashanah kulah, תאמר בפסח שאינו כשר לשמה אלא בזמנו.
tomar b'pesach she'eino kasher lishmah ela bizmano. הואיל והוא פסול לשמו—when ho'il
v'hu pasul lishmo it's not in its time it's פסול—דין הוא שיפסלו
אחרים לשמו. So
if I do the פסח pesach for the sake of another קרבן,
korban, it's פסול. pasul And if I do another קרבן korban for
the sake of פסח, pesach,
also פסול. pasul.
If חטאת chatas for the whole year is חטאת chatas for the
sake of חטאת chatas is כשר, kasher, פסח pesach for the sake
of פסח pesach all year
is—moves away—פסול. pasul. Yes, it's not a פסח pesach anymore.
Not a פסח.
pesach. עולה olah for the sake of חטאת chatas is a
possibility, but we have to explore this further.
עולה olah for the sake of פסח pesach is פסול. pasul. And
then
since the פסח pesach offering is פסול pasul. when it's brought for
its own sake during the rest of the year, then it's logical
that other offerings should be disqualified when sacrificed for its sake at
its designated time. Like this
is—פסח pesach can only be done at the time of פסח pesach
and all other time it's פסול. pasul
And so the חטאת, chatas, חטאת chatas at all times. Okay, we're
picking up again from the משנה. mishnah. The margin says... Okay. שמעון
אחי עזריה אומר. Shimon achi Azaryah omer. Let's see what he's אומר.
omer. שחטן, sh'chatan, this is back in the משנה mishnah on דף
ב' עמוד א'. daf beis amud aleph. שחטן לשם גבוה מהן כשרים,
לשם נמוך מהן פסולים. sh'chatan l'shem gavoha meihen k'sheirim, l'shem namuch meihen
p'sulim. So
we have hierarchy in the קרבנות. korbanos. If we bring a קרבן
korban that's considered נמוך namuch and we want to make it a
higher,
higher-higher, it's כשר. kasher. But if we want to take a higher
one and take it down, no. How do we know? רב אשי
מתני משמיה דרבי יוחנן ורב אחא בריה דרבא מתני משמיה דרבי ינאי.
Rav Ashi matni mishmei d'Rabi Yochanan v'Rav Acha brei d'Rava matni mishmei
d'Rabi Yannai. מאי טעמא דשמעון אחי עזריה דאמר קרא? Mai ta'ama d'Shimon
achi Azaryah d'amar kra? So we have this teaching that one teaches
in the name of the other, and what is the טעם, ta'am,
what is the reason for this opinion of שמעון אחי עזריה Shimon
achi Azaryah with the hierarchy and the traffic inside this hierarchy from
up,
from down to up, yes, from up to down, no. Because in
ויקרא Vayikra twenty-two fifteen it says, ולא יחללו את קדשי בני ישראל
את אשר ירימו לה'. v'lo y'chal'lu es kodshei bnei Yisrael es asher
yarimu l'Hashem. במורם מהם אין מתחללים, בנמוך מהם מתחללים.
bimuram meihen ein
mitchal'lim, b'namuch meihen mitchal'lim.
So we have a פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says,
and they shall not desecrate the holy things of the children of
Israel that they shall set apart for Hashem. the children of Israel
which they will, this translation says set apart unto השם *Hashem*, but
what is important in the discussion coming up is that ירימו *yarimu*
is from to lift up, right תרומה *terumah*, to lift up and
in a future tense. Okay.
והאי להכי הוא
דאתא *V'hai l'hachi hu d'ata*? Is this what this comes to teach?
והמיבעי ליה לכדשמואל *V'hamibaei leh l'ch'Shmuel*? Is it not necessary for שמואל
*Shmuel*'s derivation? דאמר שמואל מנין לאוכל את הטבל שהוא במיתה שנאמר ולא
יחללו את קדשי בני ישראל אשר ירימו לה' בעתידים לתרום הכתוב מדבר
*D'amar
Shmuel minayin l'ochel et ha-tevel she-hu b'mitah shene'emar v'lo yechalelu et kodshei
bnei Yisrael asher yarimu l'Hashem ba-atidim litrom hakatuv medaber*. So שמואל *Shmuel*
teaches us in another place that from where it is derived that
one that eats the טבל *tevel*, the untithed produce, is חייב מיתה
*chayav mitah* from the same פסוק *pasuk*, ולא יחללו את קדשי בני
ישראל אשר ירימו לה' *v'lo yechalelu et kodshei bnei Yisrael asher yarimu
l'Hashem*. They should not desecrate the holy things of the children of
Israel which they, okay, ירימו לה' *yarimu l'Hashem*.
That's what רש"י *Rashi* to the חומש *Chumash* says. He takes that
opinion in his commentary.
Say, האכילם
לזרים *ha-achilam l'zarim*.
To feed them to
non-כהנים *Kohanim*, yeah.
To make it not קדוש *kadosh*, right, to be מחלל *mechallel*, to
take it away from the קדושה *kedushah*. Yeah, that's what רש"י *Rashi*
takes there. Okay. But so now,
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is bothered by here is the tense
of the verb ירימו *yarimu* because it should be in the future.
If we're talking about things that happened, אם כן *im ken*, לכתוב
קרא *lichtov kra* אשר הורמו *asher hurmu*. It should have been said
things that have been
brought. This
shouldn't be מחולל *mechullal*. מאי אשר ירימו *Mai asher yarimu*? What is
the meaning 'will be' in the future? שמע מינה תרתי *Shma mina
tartei*. We can learn two things from it, to the past and
to the future.
It's interesting, right? Sometimes we're like no, we need three words in
order to learn three things and sometimes we can learn from one
thing two different things.
Yes, okay, so we can learn both these things about the טבל
*tevel* and about the offering that has to be sanctified. Okay. בעי
רבי זירא *Ba'ei Rabbi Zeira*. רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* raises for us
a dilemma. כשרין ואין מרצין וכי פליג בחדא פליג *Ksherin v'ein mirtzin
v'chi palig b'chada palig*.
So according to שמעון *Shimon* the brother of עזריה *Azariah*, who told
us that the less, right, the less for the more is okay,
but more for the less is not okay, more in holiness for
the less in holiness is not okay.
Not sure how to translate מרצין *mirtzin*. I have a translation but
I don't have a feeling. It's like to be accepted, right, רצה
השם *retzeh Hashem* to be accepted by השם *Hashem*. Okay.
Okay, so we have things that are כשר kashair. *kasher* but they
don't,
whatever,
they're not accepted, right, they don't fulfill the owner's obligation. This is
what we mentioned earlier. Right, so if so, when שמעון *Shimon* the
אח עזריה *Ach Azariah*
disagrees, right, with the first תנא *Tanna* of the משנה mishna *Mishnah*,
disagrees only with regards to one matter, פליג בחדא פליג *palig b'chada
palig*. או דילמא כשרין ומרצין ובתרתי פליג *O dilma ksherin u'mirtzin
u'v'tartei palig*. But
what
about alternatively, maybe שמעון *Shimon* the אח עזריה *Ach Azariah*, if he
holds that if a lesser offerings are sacrificed for the sake of
a more sacred offering, then they can be both כשר kashair *kasher*
and מרצה meratzeh. *mertzeh*. This is this little possibility here, the three-way
sudoku. Okay, and then they disagree with the Rabbis about two matters,
one is כשר kashair *kasher* and מרצה meratzeh. *mertzeh* and one is
כשר kashair *kasher* and not מרצה *mertzeh*. Okay.
So now we have another example. אמר אביי ואיתימא רבי זריקא *Amar
Abaye v'itayma Rabbi Zrika*. Interesting name, זריקא *Zrika*, because the זריקה *zrikah*...
Though he has an אלף, but yes. Yeah. Long conversation. תא שמע.
Ta shema. הבכור והמעשר ששחטן לשם שלמים כשרים. Habechor vehama'aser sheshechatan leshem
shelamim kshairim. שלמים ששחטן לשם בכור או לשם מעשר פסולים. Shelamim sheshechatan
leshem bechor o leshem ma'aser p'sulim.
So again not sure how to draw it inside our our little
thing here. Don't want to mess it up more, but okay. The
בכור, bechor, right, the firstborn animal and the מעשר, ma'aser, the tithes
animal, if it's brought for the sake of שלמים, shelamim, then it's
כשר. kashair. But if שלמים shelamim are done for the sake of
the בכור bechor or for the sake of the tithing, then it's
פסול. pasul. ואי
סלקא דעתך כשרים ומרצים, Ve'isalkadaitach kshairin u'meratzin, בכור בר ריצוי הוא? bechor
bar ritzuy hu? אלא כשרים ואין מרצים. Ella kshairin ve'ain meratzin. So
what it enters your mind that this is for the sake of
being both fit and pleasing
for
God, right? Then is a is a firstborn offering an offer that
is like בר ריצוי? bar ritzuy? Is it possible to please? No,
it is כשר and not
the translation of the ריצוי ritzuy is not not flowing.
Affect acceptance.
Acceptance. Yes, right.
Okay. Sacrificing the בכור bechor does not serve in order to be
for acceptance to affect acceptance.
In other
words, to fulfill
it like you
said, fulfill its obligation right here. Okay.
Rather,
ומדסיפא כשרים ואין מרצים. umideiseifa kshairin ve'ain meratzin. So from we learn
that from the end, this is כשר but not מרצה. הרישא נמי
כשרים ואין מרצים. Hareisha nami kshairin ve'ain meratzin. We can also infer
from the beginning that since that this is something that is כשר
and is not מרצה.
Okay. מידי איריא? Midi irya? איריא, Iriya, sorry.
I would love to get to the next משנה mishna, if possible,
which is right...
Well if we can do it in about two minutes. Two minutes.
We're already running late. Yeah, we should just go for it.
Just read it. מידי איריא? Midi irya? הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא. Ha
kideita veha kideita. So are the cases like comparable? Yes, the בכור
bechor and the מעשר ma'aser are not
ריצוי, ritzuy, are not accepted like the שלמים. shelamim. אלא מאי קא
משמע לן? Ella mai kamashmalan? גבוה ונמוך קא משמע לן תנינא. Gavoha
venamuch kamashmalan tnina. So it's like we already gave an example. What
is your what is your example? כיצד? Keitzad? קדשי קדשים ששחטן לשם
קדשים קלים. Kodesh kodashim sheshechatan leshem kodashim kalim. Again, how
the from up to down פסול, psul. from down to up כשר.
מהו
דתימא,
Mah u deiseima,
קדשי קדשים וקדשים קלים kodesh kodashim vekodashim kalim הוא דאיכא hu deika
גבוה ונמוך, gavoha venamuch, אבל קלים וקלים לא. aval kalim vekalim lo.
Okay, so we can't the we can't make parallels from lower ones
to one another but we can between the in the hierarchy between
the higher and the lower. הני נמי תנינא. Hana nami tnina. We
also have we have an objection to this. שלמים קודמים את הבכור
מפני שהן טעונים מתן ארבע Shelamim kodmim et habechor mipnei shehen te'unim
matan arba וסמיכה ונסכים ותנופת חזה ושוק. u'smicha u'nesachim u'tnufat chazeh v'shok.
There are עבודות, avodot, there are works that we do in the
שלמים shelamim that don't are not needed in the בכור. bechor.
And we are mentioning the what are the works and we'll come
to it so excitingly on page 89 when we get there בעזרת
השם. be'ezrat hashem. העיקר? Ha'ikar? ההיא אגרארה נסבה. Hahi agrareh nasva. So
the גמרא answers the primary mention of the distinction is in this
משנה, mishna, the what we dealt with right now with the hierarchy
between the sacrifices and that will be important.
That משנה, mishna the other משנה that we're not yet in there,
it cites it like incidentally in discussing order of precedences of
offerings. Like if the כהן kohen comes to the מקדש mikdash and
there's two offerings, what should he do first? How does he make
a decision what comes before what? And tomorrow we will learn more
about פסח. Pesach. יישר כח.
Yashar koach. Thank you.
Thank you. Everybody have a fabulous day.
Some kind of connection between
the two discussions.